NAACP SCHENECTADY BRANCH RECORDS (APAP028) 1949-1982
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
NAACP Schenectady Branch Records1949-1982
nam_apap028
Records document concerns for discrimination in housing and employment and for the recruitment of black professionals from colleges and universities to the area. The records also show the Branch's involvement with area social service providers, labor unions, and other community organizations, as well as with General Electric, as the area's major employer.
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Schenectady Branch.
4
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
Administrative History
The Schenectady Branch of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People was founded in 1949 by an interracial group of men and women committed to the task of improving the status of Blacks in the Schenectady community. The first ten years of the Branch's activity were characterized by strong committee work in the areas of housing and employment. Committee work was focused on ameliorating discrimination in housing and hiring practices. At the National conventions of 1952 and 1953, the Branch was honored with the Thalheimer Award for outstanding performance in the elimination of discrimination in public housing.
The NAACP Schenectady (New York) Branch worked to eliminate discrimination against workers in local industry in a variety of ways, notably functioning as a clearinghouse for applicants and employers during the 1950s when many areas of employment were effectively closed to Blacks in Schenectady. At the same time, the Branch reached out to colleges and universities to recruit young Black professionals to the area. The 1970s saw the Branch reaching out into the community in new ways in order to keep interest in the group high. This activity included close contact with area social service providers and other community organizations. Internal branch problems surfaced at this time also, resulting in some dissipation of energies.
As a research source for investigating the status of race relations in a medium sized northern city, the records of the Schenectady Branch of the NAACP will be of some value. The presence of General Electric as a major employer in the city and a strong union presence sheds some light on race matters in labor as well as NAACP relations with socialist influenced groups. Systematic initiatives in housing and employment emanated from the local Branch from the time of its inception. Executive Committee files from the 1950s detail these initiatives.
The role of women in activist organizations and in civil rights work can be explored in these records through qualitative analysis of duties performed, often in membership drives and other outreach initiatives, fundraising events and organizational support. The Branch elected its first female President in 1959, Mrs. Malinda Myers.
Scope and Content Information
Records include Executive Committee minutes, 1949-1982 (missing December 1959-January 1963); membership meeting minutes, 1949-1980 (missing January 1963-1972, 1973 [only one meeting found], 1974, October 1975-April 1976); membership lists, 1949-1980; correspondence, 1949-1980; financial records, 1949-1979 (missing 1960-1962, 1966-1976).
The role of women in activist organizations and in civil rights work can be explored in these records through qualitative analysis of duties performed, often in membership drives and other outreach initiatives, fundraising events and organizational support. The Branch elected its first female President in 1959, Mrs. Malinda Myers.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into 6 topical series.
Acquisition Information
The records were received from Joseph Allen, President of the NAACP Schenectady (New York) Branch. These records were lent to Dr. Gerald Zahavi as part of the Schenectady General Electric in the Twentieth Century Project with the understanding that the records would be microfilmed for addition to the Archives of Public Affairs and Policy of the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives. The records were received by the University Libraries in October 1994. The records were organized with funding support from the Schenectady General Electric in the Twentieth Century Project and microfilmed with funding support from the Capital District Black History Project. The original records were returned to Joseph Allen after microfilming was completed. 1994 October
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Subject and Genre Headings
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Schenectady Branch.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People -- Archives.; African Americans -- Civil rights -- History -- 20th century -- Sources.; African Americans -- Civil rights -- New York (State) -- History -- Sources.; African Americans -- Housing -- New York (State).; Civil rights -- New York (State).; African Americans -- New York (State) -- Schenectady.; African Americans -- Employment -- New York (State).; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Ethnic Groups; Schenectady, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Minutes; Letters; Registers; Reports
Container List
- Executive Committee Minutes, 1949-1982; 1
  Missing Years: Dec. 1959-Jan. 1963, May. 1964-Sept. 1973
  The Executive Committee minutes document the proceedings of the Branch's Executive Committee meetings and include Board member and officer lists, committee reports, motions and resolutions and program and budget proposals. The Branch represented the interests of African Americans in social, political and legal issues. Members of the Executive Committee directed the Branch activities under the influences of local constraints and immediate community needs and the direction of the National office and National campaigns. Discrimination in public housing and in municipal hiring practices were early targets for legalistic attacks. Community outreach and interaction with area civic, labor and religious groups provided local support for the broadest social and educational aims including non discriminatory hiring by local private businesses.
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1949; - Recognition of Schenectady Branch by State Office - Political Action re: execution of Negro prisoners in New Jersey - Approach local candidates about housing problems of African-American Schenectady citizens (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1949 December-1950 October; Segregation: a) legal action, b) branch recommendation that a Negro be appointed to the Municipal Housing Authority, c) public housing placement efforts,d) segregation of public recreational facilities - Job Discrimination - Political Action: a) petition Senator Kearney for civil rights legislation, b) letter writing campaign supporting FEPC - Legal Defense Initiatives (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1951 July-1954 December; - Communist Organizations and the NAACP - Segregation: a) housing; community outreach for Negro appointment to the MHA, b) initiative to enlist Federal support in MHA problem - Employment: initiative to place Negroes in local companies; a) General Electric - Educational Equality, campaign for: a) vocational programs, b) community education program, c) Negro History Week, d) resolution praising Supreme Court decision in Brown v. Board of Education - Political Action: a) protest to President Eisenhower and New York State Senators against the appointment of Governor Byrne to Ambassador to the United Nations (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1955; - Political Action: express constituent support of legislative measures addressing a) discrimination in public housing and initiatives to prohibit discrimination in Federal Housing Authority funded housing, b) the need to investigate discrimination in private housing, c) study of area slums, d) enforcement of anti-discrimination measures - Communist Organizations and the NAACP: communist organization activities in Schenectady and expulsion of members from Schenectady NAACP - Housing: Telephone survey by NAACP members of local landlords re: attitudes toward and willingness to rent to Black tenants - Community Outreach: Outreach efforts on race relations (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1956 January-1958 September; - Educational Equality - Housing: housing code violations - Political Action: constituent support for Metcalfe-Baker Bill Report from the US South - Youth Work (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1958 October-1959 November; - Community Outreach - Political Action: a) letter to Gov. Harriman re: discrimination from labor unions, b) support efforts for Metcalfe-Baker Bill (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1963 January-1964 April; - Officer and Committee chair list - Community Outreach: outreach through local churches - Education: a) racial imbalance in area schools, de facto segregation, b) disparate facilities, c) State Conferences call for one day boycott of school - Housing: anti-discrimination ordinances for Schenectady housing - Political Action: a) committee analysis of pending civil rights legislation, b) letter writing campaign to legislators and news releases in support of the civil rights bill - Voter Registration (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1973 September-1975 December; - Education: a) status of Black teachers in the area, b) racial imbalance persists in area schools, c) Boston bussing crisis - Employment: discrimination in hiring for Schenectady Police Force - Internal branch problems (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1976; - Employment: minority hiring in civil service - Internal branch problems - Voter Registration (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1977; - Internal branch problems (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1978; - Internal branch business: a) new office space at 214 Broadway, b) relations with National office (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1979; - Affirmative Action: Schenectady Police Department - Campaign for Martin Luther King Jr. legal holiday (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1980; - Internal branch business - Political Action (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1981 April-1982 November; - Community Watch Program - Internal branch business - Response to Neo-Nazi Activity (Reel 1)
- Membership Meeting Minutes, 1949-1980; 2
  No Minutes exist for Jan. 1963-1972, 1973 (only one meeting found), 1974 and Oct. 1975-Apr. 1976.
  Much of the content of the Members Meeting minutes closely parallels the initiatives reported in the Executive Committee meeting minutes, therefore, detailed contents notes are omitted. Reports presented as part of a meeting's minutes and provided as paper copy are included in the file with those minutes.
  The Membership Meeting Minutes document the proceedings of the members' meetings including committee reports, outreach proposals and motions and resolutions from the rank and file membership of the Branch. The Branch presented a speakers' series and planned and executed special community events for outreach and fundraising. Women often managed fundraising functions. Close adherence to the campaigns of NAACP National and to its organizational procedure characterized the direction of the membership's activities. Affiliation of members with local, professional, religious and educational organizations is evident in the proceedings and programs followed.
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1949 (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1949 December-1951 February (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1951 (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1952 January-1955 November (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1956 January -1957 March (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1957 April-1959 May (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1960 (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1961-1962 (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1973; - Only one meeting found (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1974 (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1975 (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1976 (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1977 (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1978; - Branch reorganization (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1979 (Reel 1)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes, 1980 January (Reel 1)
- Membership Lists, 1949-1980; 3
  These files contain the names, addresses, and dues paid by Branch members. Also included in the file are routine correspondence and membership reports to the National Membership Secretary in New York, New York.
  - Membership Lists, 1952 (Reel 2)
  - Membership Lists, 1954 (Reel 2)
  - Membership Reports, 1949-1958 (Reel 2)
  - Membership Reports, 1962 (Reel 2)
  - Membership Reports, 1974-1975 (Reel 2)
  - Membership Reports, 1976 (Reel 2)
  - Membership Lists and Reports, 1977-1978 (Reel 2)
  - Membership Lists and Reports, 1979 (Reel 2)
  - Membership List, 1980 (Reel 2)
- Correspondence, 1949-1980; 4
  Missing Correspondence for years, 1964-1974.
  For miscellaneous correspondence of Edward Gamarekian, founding member of the Executive Board, see Series V: Subject Files under Gamarekian.
  The Branch correspondence reflects interaction with local labor organizations, elected officials, and church and civic groups. Correspondence with NAACP National included routine business as well as the Branch's requests for guidance regarding, administration, leadership, organizational solidarity and Branch activities. Correspondence from Thurgood Marshall is notable. Local businesses corresponded with the Branch to inform members of equal opportunity employment. Public and private human services providers also corresponded frequently with the Branch, especially in the latter years of the 1970s. Correspondence of Edward Gamarekian, a founding member of the Executive Committee, is found under Gamarekian in Series 5: Subject Files.
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1949-1964; - "Blacklisting" of United Electrical Radio and Machine Workers of America; question addressed by Thurgood Marshall, Jan. 10, 1950 - Employment: Professional placement campaign - Political Action: a) Memo to all Branch offices re: Senator L.B. Johnson civil rights proposal, b) Senator Kenneth B. Keating in support of civil rights legislation (Reel 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1949-1964; - expulsion of communists, memoranda, 1951, 1952 (Reel 2)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Reel 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Reel 2)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1977; - response to the Schenectady Branch campaign to bar the name "Sambo's" from an area restaurant. Name change affirmed by Regional Director of Sambo's. (Reel 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977; - Request of Branch for assistance from National Director Benjamin Hooks in resolving internal branch problems, Nov. 10, 1977 (Reel 2)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1978; - Re-organization of Schenectady Branch, Feb. 1, 1978 - Requests for NAACP inquiries in local grievances, October 1978 (Reel 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978; - Political Action: mailgram campaign in support of Humphrey-Hawkins Bill HR50, Mar. 3, 1978 (Reel 2)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1979; - City of Schenectady Affirmative Action Task Force first meeting Apr. 30, 1979 - Employment: job postings (Reel 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1979 (Reel 3)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1980 (Reel 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1980; - Branch President complaint of harassment by an on-duty police officer (Reel 3)
  - Executive Committee "Call to Meeting" Announcements, 1980 (Reel 3)
- Subject Files, 1949-1981; 5
  The Subject Files contain records of Branch programs, committee work, news clippings and files on the careers of certain Branch members and officers. The Subject Files are organized alphabetically and span the entire period of 1949 through 1981 though the period of the 1970s is more heavily represented. The files include research on local housing conditions among Schenectady's black population in 1960. Local discrimination grievance cases are included.
  - Act-So (Afro-American Cultural, Technological Scientific Olympics), 1979 (Reel 3)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1979 (Reel 3)
  - Affirmative Action: Schenectady Police Department, 1979 (Reel 3)
  - Allmond v. Workshop discrimination investigation, 1977 (Reel 3)
  - Art Center Theatre of Schenectady, 1980 (Reel 3)
  - Black and Hispanic Political Caucus, 1980 (Reel 3)
  - Chapter Applications (misc. doc. forms), Undated (Reel 3)
  - Cintron, N.: employment matter, 1978 (Reel 3)
  - Community Outreach (miscellaneous), 1950-1970s (Reel 3)
  - Conferences of Branches, New York State, 1979 (Reel 3)
  - Conventions, National, 1959; 1978 (Reel 3)
  - Education (miscellaneous documents, scattered years), ca. 1964-1970s (Reel 3)
  - Employment, ca. 1970s (Reel 3)
  - Fair Housing Plan, 1979 (Reel 3)
  - Funding: CETA, 1979 (Reel 3)
  - Fundraising, 1954; 1978; 1979 (Reel 3)
  - Gamarekian, Edward, founding member of the Executive Board of the NAACP Schenectady Branch, 1949-1953 (Reel 3)
  - Grievances Cases, 1978; 1979 (Reel 3)
  - Historical (incomplete), 1949-1975 (Reel 3)
  - Housing, discrimination, surveys (Union College Social Research Center), 1951; 1960; 1973 (Reel 3)
  - Housing, desegregation by the Municipal Housing Authority, 1951; 1952; 1959 (Reel 3)
  - IUE-UE, memorandum, 1951 (Reel 3)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. Day Observances, 1975; 1977; 1978; 1979 (Reel 3)
  - Labor and Industry, 1978 (Reel 3)
  - LeFlore, Marzella, resume, 1978 (Reel 3)
  - May 17 Observances, 1979 (Reel 3)
  - Membership Drives, 1959; 1992 (Reel 3)
  - Mississippi Project, Freedom Summer, 1964 (Reel 3)
  - Myers, Malinda, first female Schenectady Branch president, resume, 1979 (Reel 3)
  - Newsletter, Branch, 1951; 1952; 1977 (Reel 3)
  - Newspaper clippings (Miscellaneous topics), 1951-1982 (Reel 3)
  - Political Action (incomplete), 1964; 1977; 1978; 1979; 1980 (Reel 4)
  - Poverty Program, 1964 (Reel 4)
  - Press Releases, 1977-1980 (Reel 4)
  - Press/Publicity Committee, 1977 (Reel 4)
  - Program Committee, 1958 (Reel 4)
  - Reorganization, 1977 (Reel 4)
  - "Sambo" restaurant demonstration, 1977 (Reel 4)
  - Schenectady Branch, Constitution and By-laws, 1952; 1977 (Reel 4)
  - Speeches; meeting submissions, 1952 (Reel 4)
  - State Association assessments, 1979 (Reel 4)
  - Thomas, Willis, 1975-1978 (Reel 4)
  - Town Meeting Radio Program, 1951 (Reel 4)
  - WAST T.V., 1979 (Reel 4)
  - Youth, Youth Work (see branch newsletters), 1952; 1964; 1977 (Reel 4)
  - Zuber, Paul, 1978 (Reel 4)
- Financial Records, 1949-1979; 6
  Missing Years: 1960-1962, 1966-1976
  The Financial Records include proposed budgets, financial statements, audits (1976 and 1978), revenue and fundraising reports, and records of membership dues paid.
  - Financial Statements, 1949-1959 (Reel 4)
  - Reports to the Treasurer, 1963 (Reel 4)
  - Financial Statements, 1964 (Reel 4)
  - Reports to the Treasurer, 1965 (Reel 4)
  - Audit, 1976 (Reel 4)
  - Financial Statements, 1976-1978 (Reel 4)
  - Treasurer's Journal, 1977-1979 (Reel 4)
  - Audit, 1978 (Reel 4)
  - Financial Statements, 1979 March-1981 January (Reel 4)